<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
            <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>List of ephebes participating in the second Pythaïs</title>
                        <editor xml:id="wbb"><persName>WANG Banban</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <authority>Attic Inscriptions Online in Delphi</authority>
                        <idno type="filename">FD3_2_24</idno>
                        <idno type="projectNo">1</idno>
                        <availability>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attributions-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                <repository ref="737+106+730+732+7469">737+106+730+732+7469
                                </repository> 
                                <idno type="invNo"/>
                            </msIdentifier>
                            <msContents><summary corresp="#treaty">List of Names</summary></msContents>
                            <physDesc>
                                <objectDesc>
                                    <supportDesc>
                                        <support><objectType ref="#stele">Block, Wall</objectType>
                                            <dimensions><width/><depth/><height/></dimensions></support>
                                    </supportDesc>
                                    <layoutDesc>
                                        <layout/>
                                    </layoutDesc>
                                </objectDesc>
                                <handDesc>
                                    <handNote><height/></handNote>
                                </handDesc>
                            </physDesc>
                            <history>
                                <origin>
                                    <origPlace ref="#praisos">Delphi</origPlace>
                                    <origDate period="#hellenistic" notBefore="-0230" notAfter="-0200">128/127 BCE</origDate>
                                </origin>
                            </history>
                        </msDesc>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                    <change when="2022-08-03" who="#wbb">added</change>
                    <change when="2022-08-23" who="#wbb">completed</change>
                </revisionDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            <text>
                <body xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace">
  <div xml:lang="en" type="translation" xml:space="preserve">
    <div n="1" type="textpart">
        <p>
          <lb/>God. Good Fortune.<note type="footnote">1</note>
          <lb/><term target="ephēbeusantes" xml:lang="grc-Latn">Those who were ephebes</term> in the archonship of Dionysios <note type="inline">(128/7)</note> after Lykiskos in Athens, when the priest of
          <lb/>Apollo was Eumelos son of Noumenios of Athens,<note type="footnote">2</note> when the <term target="stratēgountos epi ta hopla" xml:lang="grc-Latn">hoplite general</term> was The
          <lb break="no"/>ophrastos son of Herakleitos of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579842">Acharnai</placeName>, and (the general) of the fleet was Hipparchos son of Timokles
          <lb/><milestone unit="line" n="5"/>of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/580062">Piraeus</placeName>, and (the general) of cavalry was Diokles son of Diokles of Athens, and the <term target="phularchountōn" xml:lang="grc-Latn">tribal cavalry commanders</term> were
          <lb/>Hermon son of Dionysios, <add place="above">but by birth son of Antiphon</add> of Athens,<note type="footnote">3</note> Hagias son of Boulon of Athens, Charikles son of Theo
          <lb break="no"/>doros of Athens, Xenokles son of Demetrios of Athens, and (the general) in charge of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/580062">Piraeus</placeName> was Pyrrhinos
          <lb/>son of Athenagoras of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579998">Kydantidai</placeName>, (the general) in charge of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579920">Eleusis</placeName> was Epiphanes son of Hippakos of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/580009">Lamptrai</placeName>,<note type="footnote">4</note>
          <lb/><term target="exēgētou puthochrēstou" xml:lang="grc-Latn">the Pythochrestos interpreter</term> was Ophelas son of Habron of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579892">Bate</placeName>,<note type="footnote">5</note> and <term target="kosmētou" xml:lang="grc-Latn">superintendent</term> was Apollo
          <lb break="no"/><milestone unit="line" n="10"/>nios son of Apollonios of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/580107">Sounion</placeName>, having led the Pythais with the teachers<note type="footnote">6</note>
          <lb/>the <term target="paidotribou" xml:lang="grc-Latn">trainer</term> Nikon son of Alexis of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/678060">Berytos</placeName>, the <term target="hoplomachou" xml:lang="grc-Latn">weapons trainer</term> Sodates son of Soteles 
          <lb/>of Soloi, the <term target="akontistou" xml:lang="grc-Latn">javelin trainer</term> Nikandros son of Demetrios of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579932">Euonymon</placeName>, the <term target="toxotou" xml:lang="grc-Latn">archery trainer</term> Pystilos son of 
		      <lb/>Nikis of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/580038">Oe</placeName>, the <term target="grammateōs" xml:lang="grc-Latn">secretary</term> Tharrhinos son of Tharrhikos of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/580009">Lamptrai</placeName>, <term target="hupēretou" xml:lang="grc-Latn">attendant</term> Hieron
		      <lb/>son of Herakleides of <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/579863">Anagyrous</placeName>, <term target="hupooplomarchou" xml:lang="grc-Latn">deputy weapons trainer</term> Artemidoros son of Neon 
		      <lb/><milestone unit="line" n="15"/>of Tarsos, (made) a <term target="charistērion" xml:lang="grc-Latn">thanks-offering</term> to Apollo.
		      <lb/><space quantity="-1" unit="character"/>The <term target="tarantinarchountōn" xml:lang="grc-Latn">Tarantine cavalry commanders</term> were Diogenes son of Aropos (and) Lyson son of Demokrates,<note type="footnote">7</note>
		      <lb/><space quantity="16" unit="character"/>(ephebes) of the Athenians:
        </p>
    </div>
    <div n="1" subtype="column" type="textpart">
      <p>
        <lb/>Tharsytas son of Menedemos
        <lb/>Chares son of Chares
        <lb/><milestone unit="line" n="20"/>Kephisodoros son of Demetrios
        <lb/>Pythilas son of Apollonios
        <lb/>Philon son of Philon
        <lb/>Aristonikos son of Lysimachos
        <lb/>Hestiaios son of Philokratos
        <lb/><milestone unit="line" n="25"/>Demetrios son of Zenon
        <lb/>Diophantos son of Demetrios
        <lb/>Miltiades son of Miltiades
        <lb/>Dioskourides son of Dionysios
        <lb/>Diodotos son of Herakleides
        <lb/><milestone unit="line" n="30"/>Dioskourides son of Aristokles
        <lb/>Kleomenes son of Theodoros
        <lb/>Telesias son of Timomachos
        <lb/>Asklepiodotos son of Iason
        <lb/><gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="line"/>
        <lb/><gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character" precision="low"/>os son of Diognetos
        <lb/>Okymenes son of Okymenes
        <lb/>Pyrrhos son of Demokleides
        <lb/>Plistias son of Dionysios
        <lb/>Diogenes son of Diogenes
        <lb/>Neon son of Philokrates
        <lb/>Apollodoros son of Apollodoros
        <lb/>Attalos son of Adrastos
        <lb/>Dionysios son of Dionysios
        <lb/>Aristoboulos son of Aristoboulos 
        <lb/>Sosandros son of Nikostratos
        <lb/>Olympos son of Metrodoros
        <lb/>Spartakos son of Spartokos
        <lb/>Menodoros son of Herakleides
      </p>
    </div>
    <div n="2" subtype="subcolumn" type="textpart">
      <p>
        <lb/>Agathokles son of -
        <lb/>Demetrios son of De-
        <lb/>Nikias son of Euphemides
        <lb/>Diodotos son of Philostratos
        <lb/>Aristodamas son of Ariston
        <lb/>Dinokles son of Philostratos
        <lb/>Dionysios son of Diogenes
        <lb/>Lysimachos son of Philoxenos
        <lb/>Philemon son of Lenaios
        <lb/>Antimachos son of Nikias
        <lb/>Dexitheos son of Dexitheos
        <lb/>Athenobios son of Athenodoros
        <lb/>Athenagoras son of Pyrrhinos
        <lb/>Mousaios son of Euegoros
        <lb/>Menodoros son of Diogenes
        <lb/>Apollodotos son of Sthenios
        <lb/>- son of Dionysios
        <lb/><gap reason="illegible"/> son of -mos
        <lb/>Nikanor son of Demeas
        <lb/>Timokrates son of Alexandros
        <lb/>Chairokles son of Chairokles
        <lb/>Timokles son of Demokleides
        <lb/>Charmides son of Paramonos
        <lb/>Polyainetos son of Amyklas<!-- V2-52945, perhaps a multi-gen immigrant from Istros or Thasos? -->
        <lb/>Onesiphilos son of Philon
        <lb/>Diodoros son of Diodoros 
        <lb/>Phontides son of Hipparchos 
        <lb/>Sosippos son of Nikanor
        <lb/>Theodoros son of Theodoros
        <lb/>Epikrates son of Aphrodisios
        <lb/>Demagoras son of Euthydoros
      </p>
    </div>
    <div n="3" subtype="subcolumn" type="textpart">
      <p>
        <lb/>Teisis son of Phi-
        <lb/>Zenodotos son of [Theod-]
        <lb/>Achaios son of Apollodoros
        <lb/>Sophilos son of Sophilos 
        <lb/>Aristion son of Eudoxos
        <lb/>Damonax son of Askondas<!-- This name was attested only once in Athens, but of all the 20 attestations in <i>LGPN</i>, 18 came from Rhodes and Cyrene; Askōndas was attested four times, with the other three all in Boiotia. -->
        <lb/>Apollonios son of Dionysios. 
        <lb/>When at Delphi <term target="gymnasiarchountos" xml:lang="grc-Latn">gymnasiarch</term>
        <lb/>was Kleomantis son of Herys <!-- Very popular name in Delphi, this Kleomantis appeared in many honorific texts in Delphi. V3b-42931. --> 
        <lb/>and the ephebes were
        <lb/>Diodoros son of Mnasitheos <!-- the father V3b-43859 is a large slave manumittor, eg sgdi 2154. -->
        <lb/>Nikias son of Aristion
        <lb/>Xenokrates son of Agesilaos <!-- he would become the archon at Delphi L87 -->
        <lb/>Xenon son of Peisitheos <!-- SGDI 2271, V3b-44429 -->
        <lb/>Phainios son of Gorgilos
        <lb/>Philinos son of Philleas <!-- FD restored as Damenēs, but this Lamenēs may be the forefather of a later archon N14, consult add. 290!! -->
        <lb/><note type="inline">six lines traces</note>
        <lb/>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:lang="en" type="commentary" xml:space="preserve">
    <p>

    !+1+ <em>Textual Note</em> AIO incorporates readings [Τεῖ]σις Φ[-] and Ζηνόδοτ[ος Θεοδ-] in col. 3, ll. 18-19 from Tracy, <i>BCH</i> 99, 1975, 192 (which by itself was based on <i>SEG</i> 15.104, col. 2, l. 223 and col. 2, l. 214 respectively); Φαίν[ι]ος τοῦ Γοργίλου | Φιλίνου τοῦ Φιλλέα in col. 3, ll. 32-33 from <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, Add. p. 290. In col. 2, l. 33, the fragmented name was restored as Ἀπολλόδοτος Σθενίου, on the basis of <i>SEG</i> 15.104, col. 1, l. 174.</br></br>
    This list of 68 ephebes, along with their instructors and officers, was inscribed on six blocks in three courses (Courses I-III) on the southern façade of the <a href="https://arachne.dainst.org/entity/5593" class="highlight">Athenian Treasury</a> shortly after the second <i>Pythais</i> of 128/7 BC (on the <i>Pythais</i> and the Treasury, see <a href="/inscriptions/inscription/FDIII2/3" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 3</a> with notes and on Attic inscriptions at Delphi, see <a href="/inscriptions/inscription/IGII34/17" class="highlight"><i>IG</i> II<sup>3</sup> 4, 17</a> with notes). The list was carved side-by-side to the right of the ephebic list of the first <i>Pythais</i> in 138/7 BC (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 23).  There are also lists from the third and fourth <i>Pythaides</i> (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 25-26). Unlike the earlier and latter texts, this inscription has a long preamble (ll. 1-17) listing important magistrates and instructors of the ephebes (see nn. 4-7), which was inscribed on the blocks of the top course. The first line was inscribed with horizontal space evenly distributed between letters. The list of ephebes is written in three columns extending over two courses, with sixteen lines of each column on the upper block, and fifteen lines on the lower. The decrees honouring the ephebes of 128/7 BC found in Athens mention the ephebes' participation in the <i>Pythais</i> (<i>SEG</i> 15.104, ll. 18-19), but state that a total of 107 young men had completed the ephebate (<i>SEG</i> 15.104, ll. 89-90, the text has space for only 94 names though). Only 68 names appear at Delphi, in which 32 names do not appear in <i>SEG</i> 15.104. S. Tracy suggests that the participation in the <i>Pythais</i> procession was mandatory to all ephebes, but that only some ephebes took measures to ensure the engraving of their names (<i>BCH</i> 99, 1975, 192). Alternatively, participation in the <i>Pythais</i> may simply have been voluntary, as some ephebes cannot be found in the Athenian ephebic decrees but was present here (see note below) or vice versa. Many of the ephebes listed here were relatives of earlier or later Pythaists (see note below) or helped to fund the fourth <i>Pythais</i> in 97/6 BC (see <i>IG</i> II<sup>2</sup> 2236 with S. Tracy, <i>IG II<sup>2</sup> 2236, Contributors of First Fruits for the Pythais</i>, 1982). Such family patterns of participation are typical of the Pythaists, see <a href="/inscription/FDIII2/12/" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 12</a> with notes, and for ephebes in particular, also T. Henderson, <i>The Springtime of the People</i>, 2020, 225-6. Like most of the <i>Pythais</i> inscriptions but unlike ephebic inscriptions in Athens (<i>SEG</i> 15.104 as an example), here ephebes are not arranged by tribe, and their demes are not specified: this corresponds to normal Athenian practice at Delphi in the second century BC when, in contrast to the third century, Athenian demes and tribes were not mentioned, as in e.g. <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 93. On the Athenian ephebate, see <a href="/inscriptions/inscription/RO/89" class="highlight">RO 89</a> with notes; on Athenian ephebate in the Hellenistic Period, see É. Perrin-Saminadayar, <i>Éducation, culture et société à Athènes</i>, 2007, 248-266 and Henderson, <i>Springtime</i>, 171-289.!

!+2+ Eumelos son of Noumenios held this priesthood in Athens. He was probably the father of Noumenios son of Eumelos, a Pythaist-boy in the first <i>Pythais</i> (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 11, l. 5, see C. Habicht, <i>Athenische Mitteilungen</i>  97, 1982, 181). In this text, six of the magistrates are named merely as 'of Athens' rather than by their demes. On Hellenistic priesthoods in Athens, see S. Lambert in M. Horster and A. Klöckner eds., <i>Civic Priests</i>, 2012, 67-133.!

!+3+ The phrase 'but by birth son of Antiphon' was added in the space between ll. 5-6. This Hermon was directly mentinoed as son of Antiphon in <a href="/inscription/FDIII2/27" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 27</a>, col. 1, l. 10.!

!+4+ This list of generals is exceptional, both for <i>Pythais</i>-related inscriptions and for ephebic decrees, in naming the civic military commanders involved in ephebic training. From the mid-fourth century BC, the generals were assigned specific competencies (cf. <a href="/inscription/IGII34/8" class="highlight"><i>IG</i> II<sup>3</sup> 4, 8</a> and <a href="/inscription/IGII34/276" class="highlight">276</a>, with notes). Three types of commanders are involved here: the generals in charge of specific forces (hoplite, fleet, cavalry), generals in charge of specific garrisons (Piraeus and Eleusis), and the tribal cavalry commanders. From the third century onwards, the hoplite general was ultimately in charge of the ephebes' training and sometimes joined them in processions (see Henderson, <i>Springtime</i>, 2020, 210-211). The generals of the fleet (<i>epi ton nautikon</i>) and the cavalry (<i>epi ton hippikon</i>) are mentioned only once ever in existing texts. The commanders of the cavalry participated in other <i>Pythaides</i> and are mentioned in lists of cavalrymen (<a href="/inscription/FDIII2/27" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 27</a> for the second, <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 28 for the third, and <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 26 for the fourth). Diokles reappears in the Delphic honorific decree for the association of cavalrymen (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 46) and the name list of cavalrymen (<a href="/inscription/FDIII2/27"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 27</a>). However, Diokles’ title here, ‘(general) of the cavalry’ (<i>epi to hippikon</i>), differs from the other two texts, where he holds the more normal title ‘cavalry commander’ (<i>hipparchos</i>). On the cavalry commander and his duties, see <a href="/inscription/IGII31/1281" class="highlight"><i>IG</i> II<sup>3</sup> 1, 1281</a> with note. This difference is rather of nomenclature than of function, as parallel interchangeability between 'general of the navy' (<i>strategos epi to nautikon</i>) and 'commander of the navy' (<i>nauarchos</i>) exists also in the second century BC (cf. W. S. Ferguson, <i>Klio</i> 9, 1909, 314-323). The generals in charge of Piraeus and Eleusis oversaw Athenian garrisons at these two posts. Ephebes served as part of the Piraeus garrison after Athens regained their control over it in 229 BC, as part of their military training, see Henderson, <i>Springtime</i>, 2020, 211-214. Ephebes also went out for excursions to countryside fortresses, Eleusis included, and participated in rituals related to the Eleusinian cult (see, e.g., sacrifice in <i>IG</i> II<sup>2</sup> 1011, ll. 7-8 and <a href="/inscription/AIUK42/17" class="highlight"><i>AIUK</i> 4.2 (BM, Decrees), 17</a> with notes). On the garrison at Eleusis, see <a href="/inscription/IEleus/207" class="highlight"><i>I Eleusis</i> 207</a>, with notes. The tribal cavalry commanders (<i>phularchoi</i>) assisted the cavalry commander (see <a href="/inscription/IGII31/949" class="highlight"><i>IG</i> II<sup>3</sup> 1, 949</a> and <a href="/inscription/IGII34/252" class="highlight"><i>IG</i> II<sup>3</sup> 4 252</a> with notes). They could also be involved in ephebic training for their tribes. They were honoured by the Delphians, together with the general of the cavalry, the Tarantine cavalry commanders and the association (<i>koinon</i>) of cavalrymen, in <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 46.!

!+5+ The <i>pythochrestes exegetes</i>, literally the 'interpreter ordained by Pythian Apollo', was appointed in Athens from the fifth century BC (<a href="/inscription/AIO/1137" class="highlight"><i>IG</i> I<sup>3</sup> 131</a>, l. 9, Pl. <i>Leg</i>. 9.865b-d). For the interpreter in Archaic and Classical Athens, see Valdés Guía, <i>Mediterraneo Antico</i> 5, 2002, esp. 190ff. Although Suda, s.v. <i>exegetai</i> claims that there were three <i>pythochrestoi</i>, whose tasks were to lift curses and to expound ancestral customs, the <i>Pythais</i> inscriptions mention only one at a time (cf. J. H. Oliver, <i>Athenian Expounders</i>, 1950, 36–46). In the Augustan period, the <i>pythochrestos exegetes</i> also appears in the <i>Dodekais</i> inscriptions (<a href="/inscription/FDIII2/59" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 59</a>, 61–64). Our interpreter here, Ophelas son of Habron of Bate, belonged to a distinguished family, with two other members serving as interpreter 'appointed by the People': Kallias son of Habron (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 5 in 106/5 BC), and Kallias son of Euktemon (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 6 in 97/6 BC); one of the <i>thesmothetai</i> who organized this <i>Pythais</i>, Euktemon son of Kallias (<a href="/inscription/FDIII2/3" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 3</a>, col. 1, l. 8) also belonged to this family.!

!+6+ The superintendent (<i>kosmetes</i>) was the annual official in charge of the ephebate, see Henderson, <i>Springtime</i>, 2020, 204, 208-9. Our superintendent here, Apollonios, was crowned the following year in the decrees honouring the ephebes of 128/7 BC (<i>SEG</i> 15.104). The formula here, the ephebes 'led the Pythais' (ἀγαγόντες τὴν Πυθαΐδα, l. 10), is different from that of two later <i>Pythais</i> inscriptions for the ephebes (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 25-26), where the ephebes are described as 'participating at the front of the Pythais' (προπέμψαντες τὴν Πυθαΐδα). Both suggest that the ephebes marched at the front of the procession. On the ephebic instructors, see Henderson, <i>Springtime</i>, 2020, 217-221. In Hellenistic Athens, the role of ephebic instructor was one of the few roles in Athenian public life that was open to foreigners (see M. Niku, <i>Official Status of the Foreign Residents in Athens</i>, 2007, 17). In this inscription, three instructors are explicitly identified as foreigners: the physical trainer (<i>paidotribēs</i>) Nikon of <a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/678060" class="highlight">Berytos</a> (modern Beirut), whose homonymous relative was an ephebe on <a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/599587" class="highlight">Delos</a> in 119/8 BC (<i>I Délos</i> 2598, col. 1, l. 9); the weapons trainer (<i>hoplomachos</i>) Sotades of (most likely the <a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/648781" class="highlight">Cilician</a>) Soloi; and Artemidoros of <a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/648789/" class="highlight">Tarsos</a> as deputy weapons trainer (<i>hupooplomachos</i>). The first two are also honoured in <i>SEG</i> 15.104, ll. 137–140, together with the javelin trainer, archery trainer, secretary, as well as the ballistic trainer (<i>aphetēs</i>) and the official (<i>hupēretēs</i>) who did not participated in the <i>Pythais</i>.!

!+7+ The first letter of this line was indented to the left. Tarantine cavalry commander participated in the third <i>Pythais</i> (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 28). Together with the general of the cavalry, three tribal cavalry commanders, and the association (koinon) of cavalrymen, these two Tarantine cavalry commanders received honour and wreath crown from the Delphians in <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 46. For the Tarantine cavalry, see <a href="/inscription/SEG/46167" class="highlight"><i>SEG</i> 46.167</a> with notes.!

!+8+ At least two ephebes (as well as Pythaist-boys, see <a href="/inscription/FDIII2/12/" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 12</a>) in this list marched to Delphi together with their fathers or relatives who took other roles in the second <i>Pythais</i>. Here, this Chares (col. 1, l. 19) was the son of Chares (II), who participated in this <i>Pythais</i> as official visitor (<i>theoros</i>), see <a href="/inscription/FDIII2/8/" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 8</a>, col. 1, l. 9 and note. Athenagoras (col. 2, l. 30) was son of Pyrrhinos, the general in charge of Piraeus this year (l. 7).!

!+9+ Kephisodoros (col. 1, l. 20) and Aristonikos (col. 1, l. 23) participated in the first <i>Pythais</i> as Pythaist-boys in 138/7 BC (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 11, l. 19). His father Demetrios was honoured by the Delphians as one of the ‘epic poets’ (<i>epopoioi</i>) in this <i>Pythais</i> (<i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 50, l. 5). Kephisodoros was later general in charge of Piraeus (<i>SEG</i> 24.194, ll. 41-42), manager (<i>epimelētēs</i>) of Piraeus and a benefactor of the fourth <i>Pythais</i> (<i>IG</i> II<sup>2</sup> 2336, ll. 107-8). !

!+10+ Two names in this list were attested only once in all the earlier Athenian documents, but frequently appeared in other places: Spartokos son of Spartokos has a name more frequently attested around <a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/854675" class="highlight">Bosporos</a>, and Damonax son of Askondas (col. 3, l. 23) has a <a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/373778" class="highlight">Cyrenaic</a> or <a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/590030" class="highlight">Rhodian</a> name. It is likely that they can be foreign ephebes: while the ephebate in Athens was opened exclusively for young Athenian citizens in the Classical Period, it was clearly opened to foreigners at least in 122/1 BC (<i>IG</i> II<sup>2</sup> 1006+1031+2485 = <i>SEG</i> 38.114), in which 14 foreign ephebes were registered under a rubric 'foreigner' (<i>xenoi</i>). On foreign ephebes, see Henderson, <i>Springtime</i>, 267–272.!

!+11+ In order to distribute the names evenly on the lower two courses of blocks, a broad uninscribed space was left between ll. 33 and 34. As a result, 16 names appeared on the higher block and 15 on the lower block.!

!+12+ A list of names, including a gymnasiarch of Delphi, six ephebes with well-preserved names and perhaps six lost names, starts at l. 25, inscribed with no vertical gap from the previous name, but with the first letter indented to the left. The gymnasiarch, Kleomantis, is mentioned in several Delphic decrees around this period as secretary of the Council at Delphi (cf. G. Daux, <i>Chronologie delphique</i> L67, and <i>SEG</i> 27.124) and as a councillor (L68). This is the only occurrence of a Delphic gymnasiarch in Hellenistic inscriptions at Delphi (the only other attestation is <i>F.Delphes</i> III 3, 233, l. 5, dated to 80–95 AD), and the only mention of a Delphic ephebate (Cl. Vatin’s restoration in <i>BCH</i> 96, 1972, 261 n. 14 remains uncertain), although the gymnasium played an important social role in late Hellenistic Delphi (cf. <i>F.Delphes</i> II, <i>Le Gymnase</i>, 1953, 81–86). We know that some of these ephebes belonged to families that were prominent at Delphi: Diodoros son of Mnasitheos (l. 28) belonged to a rich family attested in various manumission texts from this time, Xenokrates son of Agesilaos (l. 30) would be archon of Delphi during the third <i>Pythais</i> (<i>Chronologie delphique</i> L87 = 106/5 BC).!


</p>
    </div>
  
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>