<body xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace">
  <div xml:lang="en" type="translation" xml:space="preserve">
F.Delphes III 2, 34

	Gods. For Good Fortune. In the archonship of Pyrrhos at Delphi, in Athens of
	Dionysios (128/7) after Lykiskos,+1+ having won among the tribal cavalry commanders, first+2+ 
	of those who escorted the <i>Pythais</i> with the cavalry commander (hipparchou) Diokles and his
	fellow magistrates, when Diokles son of Diokles of Athens held the contest.

Column 1
	crown to the left of the text
5	From the tribal cavalry commanders;
	Double-length race (diaulon)
	with a war
	horse:
	Hagias son of
10	Boulon of
	Athens.
	
Column 2
	crown to the left of the text
5	From the cavalry:
	Double-length race with a
	war horse: Hagias
	son of Boulon
	of Athens.

F.Delphes III 2, 35

	In the archonship of Pyrrhos at Delphi, in Athens of Dionysios (128/7) after Lykiskos, the 		following
	won among the cavalry and the tribal cavalry commanders who escorted the Pythais,
	while [the cavalry commander (hipparchou) Diokles son of Diokles] held [the contest], the leaders of the Tarantine
	cavalry being Diogenes [son of Aropos and Lyson son of Demokrates],  the tribal cavalry commanders being Hermon
5	son of Dionysios, [Hagios son of Boulon, Charikles son of] Theodoros, Xenokles
	son of Demetrios.

Column 1
7	…
	…
	…
	(crown below)

Column 2
6	From the tribal cavalry commanders:
	[double-length race]
	with a war [horse in] armour:
	[Hermon son of Dionysios] of Athens
10	[by birth son of] Antiphon.
	crown below

Column 3
6	Double-length race
	with a war horse: Hagias
	son of Boulon.
	crown below

F.Delphes III 2, 36

	Double-length race
	with a war horse: Hermon
	son of Antiphon.+3+
	crown below

F.Delphes III 2, 37

Column 1
1	Byttakos
	son of Byttakos,
	[straight race].
	crown below

Column 2
1	Zoilos son of Timokrates of Athens,
	from the cavalry, javelin throw (akōntizōn) ⟦with a Tarantine war horse
	double-length race⟧.+4+
	crown below
Column 3
1	Kallistratos
	son of Kallistratos
	of Athens, double-length race
	from the Tarantine cavalry,
5	with a war horse.
	crown below

F.Delphes III 2, 38

Column 1
	Kallitheos
	son of Lysiades
	double-length race.
	crown below

Column 2	
	Pyrrhos
	son of Pyrrhos
	straight race (akampion).+5+
	(crown below)

F.Delphes III 2, 39

Column 1
	[Straight race] :
	Charikles
	son of Theodoros.
	crown below

Column 2
	Straight race:
	Xenokles
	son of Demetrios
	of Athens.
	crown below

Column 3
	[From all: double-length]
	[race with a] war [horse]:
	Hagias [son of Boulon]
	crown below

F.Delphes III 2, 40

Column 1	
	Double-length race with horse:
	Sotion son of Nikanor
	crown below

Column 2
	Straight race:
	Charinos
	son of Lykinos
	crown below

Column 3
	From all: double-length
	race with a war
	[horse]: Dio-
	son of Diodotos of Athens.+6+
	crown below

F.Delphes III 2, 41

Column 1
	Theopeithes
	son of Theophilos
	double-length race.
	crown below

Column 2
	Diokles
	son of Diokles
	straight race
	crown below

Column 3	
	Timokles son of Hipparchos
	of Athens, from the cavalry,
	straight race.+7+
	crown below

F.Delphes III 2, 42

	From all: straight race with horse:
	Straton son of Boulon of Athens.+8+
	crown below

  </div>
  <div xml:lang="grc" type="edition" xml:space="preserve">
      <div n="1" type="textpart">
          <lb/>
          <lb/>
      </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:lang="en" type="note" xml:space="preserve">
    <p>
!+1+ <strong>Textual Note</strong> AIO includes col. 1 in <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 37 from <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, Add. pp. 290-1. <br/><br/>

This dossier honours victors at several sporting contests during the second <i>Pythais</i>, which took place in 128/7 BC. It was inscribed on various unconnected blocks on the southern façade, as well as on the front and inner sides of the south <i>anta</i> of the Athenian Treasury (on the <i>Pythais</i> and the Treasury, see <a href="/inscriptions/inscription/FDIII2/3" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 3</a> with notes, and on Attic inscriptions at Delphi, see <a href="/inscriptions/inscription/IGII34/17" class="highlight"><i>IG</i> II<sup>3</sup> 4, 17</a> with notes). The victor's names were engraved with a crown beneath them (or, in <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 34, to the left) and were mostly grouped in two or three columns, each occupying a single block on the Treasury wall. Although <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2 gives each group an individual number in an attempt to attribute one unique number to different victories engraved on the same block, it is more appropriate to treat all nine inscriptions together.  Most of the texts have only the victor's name and the contest, meaning that they can only be dated on prosopographic grounds (most of the names appear also in the list of cavalrymen at the second <i>Pythais</i>: <a href="/inscriptions/inscription/FDIII2/27" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 27</a>).  Equestrian and musical contests were held during the <i>Pythais</i> (for the musical contests, see the Delphic honorific decrees for the Dionysiac artists, <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2.47–49, and S. Kühn, <i>Pythais-Prozession</i>, 2018, 172-76). The equestrian contests of the <i>Pythais</i>, like the tribal contests at the Panathenaia (<i>IG</i> II<sup>2</sup> 2316-17) and Theseia (<i>IG</i> II<sup>2</sup> 956–958), were organized into separate divisions: tribal cavalry commanders, members of the Tarantine cavalry, and all Athenian cavalrymen (named simply as 'of all'). As in the Panatheniac contests and unlike the Olympics and other Panhellenic games, the contestants rode their own horses in the contests (cf. J. Shear, <i>Serving Athena</i>, 2021, 193-94 and table 5.14 on the Panathenaia). The contests include a javelin throw  (<i>akontizōn</i>), a straight race (<i>akampios</i>, i.e. from one end of the stadium to the other), a double-length race (<i>diaulos</i>, i.e. from one end of the stadium to the other and back), a double-length race with a war horse (<i>hippo polemiste diaulos</i>), and a double race with a war horse in armour (<i>hippo polemiste diaulos en hoplois</i>). On equestrian contests in the Hellenistic world generally, see C. Chandezon in J.-C. Moretti and P. Valavanis, <i>Les hippodromes et les concours hippiques</i>, 2020; on equestrian contests in Delphi, see S. Kühn, <i>Pythais-Prozession</i>, 2018, 168-72.!

!+2+ The expression 'as the first' (protos) suggests that Hagias may have taken the leading position among the tribal cavalry commanders during the <i>Pythais</i> procession.    According to the surviving texts, Hagias was the most successful contestant as he won four crowns, all in the double race with war horse (diaulon hippoi polemistēi) against different opponents (tribal cavalry commanders and the cavalry in <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 34; all cavalrymen in <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 39, and an unspecified division in <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 35). This indicates that some contestants were able to compete in multiple categories.!

!+3+ <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 36–38 were inscribed on three horizontally adjoining blocks, with very similar top margins.! 

!+4+ The two columns of <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 37 were inscribed by the same hand, using the same guidelines, which were incised in advance. The space which bears the word <i>akontizon</i> ('javelin throw') has traces of erased letters, and <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, p. 42 reads these as 'with Tarantine horse' (tarantinōnippōi). Analysis of the squeeze indicates that a third line in col. 2 reads 'double race with war-' (polemistei diaulon), which was also erased imperfectly.!  

!+5+ Both columns were inscribed by the same hand and connected with the same guidelines. The word diaulon ('double-length race') in col. 1, l. 3 was inscribed over an earlier text, which read akampion ('straight race').!

!+6+    <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 40, col. 1 and col. 2 were inscribed by the same hand and connected with the same guidelines. However, col. 3 is not on the same guidelines and even not aligned to the same height as the other two texts. The lost name may be Diodotos son of Diodotos of Sypalettos, who was manager (<i>epimeletes</i>) of the island Delos in 106/5 BC (<i>I Délos</i> 2234) and relative (or the same one) of the cavalryman in the third <i>Pythais</i> (106/5 BC, <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 28, col. 2, l. 30. P. Roussel, <i>Délos colonie athénienne</i>, 1916, 109-110).!

!+7+ <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 35, 39, 40, and 41   were inscribed on four horizontally adjoining blocks and have the same design, i.e. three crowns on one block (the crown below col. 1 of <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 35 is now lost). The columns of <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 41 are not aligned; col. 3 is significantly higher than the other two. As Timokrates son of Hipparchos is, not attested in the surviving cavalry list of the second <i>Pythais</i> (<a href="/inscriptions/inscription/FDIII2/27" class="highlight"><i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 27</a>), unlike the other victors, it is not certain that his victory was in 128/7 BC.!

!+8+ <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 42 was inscribed on the inner side of the south anta, on the same block as <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 34. The letters of the text are significantly smaller (ca. 7mm) than other texts in the dossier (ca. 9–10mm), but comparable to <i>F.Delphes</i> III 2, 43 (also ca. 7mm, dated to the third <i>Pythais</i> in 106/5 BC). This might then suggest that Straton won at the straight race in 106/5 BC, rather than in 128/7 BC. Though he is not otherwise attested, Straton probably was a relative of Hagias, given their identical patronym.!


    </p>
  </div>
  </body>